here on Democracy Now democracynow.org
The War and Peace report I'm Amy Goodman
with Juan Gonzalez
attorney general Jeff sessions has
announced an administration-wide
Crackdown on leaks announcing the FBI
has formed a new team specifically
focused on investigating potential leaks
to the Press during a press conference
on Friday sessions announced leak
investigations have tripled since
president Trump took office
so today I have this message for our
friends in the intelligence Community
the Department of Justice is open for
business and I have this warning for
would-be leakers don't do it
I've listened to our career
investigators FBI agents and others and
our prosecutors about how to most
successfully investigate and prosecute
these matters at their suggestion one of
the things we are doing is reviewing
policies affecting media subpoenas on
Twitter president Trump praise session
speech writing quote after many years of
leaks going on in Washington it is great
to see the AG taking action for National
Security the tougher the better unquote
Trump's new Chief of Staff John Kelly
also warns staff over the weekend about
the leaks to the Press although his
warning itself was promptly leaked
civil liberties and press Freedom groups
criticize sessions remarks then Weisner
of the ACLU said quote a Crackdown on
leaks is a Crackdown on the Free Press
and on Democracy as a whole well for
more we go to Washington D.C where we're
joined by John kiriaku spent 14 years at
the CIA as an adolescent case officer
cariako exposed the bush era torture
program and became the only official
jailed in connection with it his Memoir
is titled doing time like a spy how the
CIA taught me to survive and thrive in
prison John cariaco welcome back to
democracy Now
we spoke to when you were under house
arrest after you got out of jail and now
speaking to you now can you respond to
the attorney general Jeff sessions
yeah I think this is really not about
leaks as much as it is about controlling
the Press uh it's it's the press that
the president has a problem with uh and
another thing too that I think is very
important in this whole scenario the
intelligence Community the intelligence
agencies the Department of Defense can
refer as many leaks as they want to the
FBI it's the FBI that's going to decide
if they're even worth investigating and
even if they are worth investigating
they're still going to have to try to
figure out whether or not it's worth
filing charges so it doesn't really
matter how many new leaks are referred
to the justice department for
investigation I think we're going to see
very few actual cases if any at all and
John kiriako the aside from the uh the
trend toward constant tweeting was there
is there any basic or fundamental
difference between the way the Trump
Administration has been hand handling
leaks and the Obama Administration
frankly not much this really isn't so
much of a new policy as it is an
extension of the Obama administration's
policy it was Attorney General Eric
Holder that really declared war on leaks
back in 2009 and it was the Obama
Administration that prosecuted nearly
three times as many leak cases as all
previous administrations combined so I
think that that the Obama uh I'm sorry
that the Trump Administration is perhaps
a little bit more vocal about its
intentions but it's really not much of a
difference in policy
on Sunday Deputy attorney general Rod
Rosenstein said the Department of
Justice is not targeting journalists
this is what he said on Fox News Sunday
the Attorney General's been very clear
we're after the leakers not the
journalists we're after people who are
committing crimes and so we're going to
devote the resources we need to identify
who is responsible for those leaks and
who has violated the law and hold them
accountable what is your response to
that do you believe what um attorney
general the deputy attorney general is
saying
no I don't uh and frankly somebody
should tell the attorney general that
his Deputy is saying that this is not
going to be focused on the Press when
the Attorney General himself has has
said that it will be focused on the
Press you know I think the justice
department learned a lesson with with
James risen of the New York Times in the
Jeffrey Sterling case where they tried
to compel ryzen to testify in that case
ryzen refused uh he went to the uh to
the fourth Circuit Court of Appeals and
lost there went then to the Supreme
Court and lost there and still refused
to testify finally the justice
department backed off I think that the
Trump justice department isn't going to
want the government to back off I think
they're going to want to make an example
of somebody in the press and preferably
make an example of someone who's as
highly respected as James risen is
you've been one of several uh former
intelligence officials who've talked
about the the problem of over
classification of material in the in the
uh in the U.S government could you
elaborate on that
yes there are something like 3 billion
classified documents in U.S government
databases it's actually and most
Americans don't even realize this it's
actually illegal to over classify
something now in the CIA we saw this
kind of thing all the time and I'll give
you an example my wife and I were in the
CIA at the same time if I wanted to have
lunch with her I would send her a
message and say hey do you want to have
lunch and I would classify that document
secret now why is that secret it's
actually not secret but everybody
classified everything at the secret
level it was just policy it's just the
way things were she would respond to me
sure I'll meet you at 12 and she would
classify that secret it's actually
illegal to do that and I think that in
in what we're seeing now with with the
case that I think is the impetus of this
new Justice Department announcement the
the leak of the transcripts of President
Trump's conversations with the Prime
Minister of Australia and with the
president of of mass Mexico that the
information in those transcripts really
wasn't very sensitive it was
embarrassing to the president certainly
but it wasn't uh it had no impact on
national security so for the
administration to say that that was
classified or that that was somehow
National Security information is an over
classification
this is an issue that that no one in
government has yet addressed and I think
that the only way it will be addressed
is if someone is arrested for for
leaking this information and then they
fight it by saying that it was
improperly classified I think that's the
only way we're going to see action on
this if you're asking your wife to meet
in the evening would that be top secret
exactly I mean we throw around these
these classifications like they mean
nothing in fact they mean very important
things now what what should be used are
are things called controls rather than
classifications you can call something
sensitive but unclassified sbu or you
can call it for official use only so
that means that they're not intended for
public dissemination but they're not
necessarily classified there's a lot of
information in government that should
that should have those controls but
should not be classified and could you
discuss also the distinction between
just leaking and whistle blowing for
those folks who don't understand the
distinction
I think this is a very important
distinction actually there's a legal
definition of whistleblowing and that is
bringing to light any evidence of waste
fraud abuse illegality or threats to the
public health or Public Safety leaking
is just leaking and there are lots of
motivations for leakers some people like
the thrill of of speaking with a
journalist for example some people like
to feel important that they're on the
inside they have this information and
they just have to share it with somebody
some people do it for Revenge just
because they're angry at a boss angry at
the president perhaps angry at a
supervisor but leaking is not
whistleblowing they are mutually
exclusive and politicians and even the
White House leak all the time don't they
well you know that's the Dirty Little
Secret of Washington isn't it the most
prolific leaker in Washington is the
president of the United States not even
just that it's Donald Trump it was
Barack Obama before him uh certainly uh
many leaks I might even say most leaks
come out of the White House out of the
National Security Council and out of the
defense department now those are usually
what we call official leaks where
they're meant as trial balloons or
they're meant to influence public
opinion or public policy those leaks are
never prosecuted uh John your Memoir
doing time like a spy how the CIA taught
me to survive and thrive in prison
um can you remind us and for people who
don't know the story of John kiriaku how
you ended up serving two years in prison
what exactly you did
sure in December of 2007 I gave an
interview to Brian Ross of ABC News in
which I said three things I said that
the CIA was torturing its prisoners I
said that torture was official U.S
government policy it was not the result
of a rogue CIA officer as President Bush
had suggested and I said that the
torture policy had been personally
approved by the president himself so
within 24 hours the CIA filed a crimes
report against me and the FBI began
investigating me they investigated me
for a full year until December of 2008
and then determined that I had not
committed a crime and they closed the
case what I didn't know was that a month
later after President Obama had been
inaugurated and Eric Holder had been
named attorney general that the CIA
asked holder to secretly reopen the case
against me and so the FBI investigated
me for another three years until January
of 2012. now in that three-year period
the FBI dug deep into my life they
tapped my phones they intercepted my
emails I was under surveillance I had no
idea any of that was taking place and
they found an email that I had sent in
which a reporter asked me if I would
introduce him to someone who might agree
to sit for an interview for a book he
was writing
I in my response I confirmed the last
name of a former CIA colleague who I
believed was was retired that was a
crime that was a violation of the
intelligence identities protection act
but I wasn't just charged with that I
was also charged with three counts of
Espionage coming out of my original ABC
news interview and one kind of making a
false statement which my attorneys and I
never really fully understood I I didn't
really know what the false statement was
but in any event
um
I always believed and my attorneys
believed that that my case was not about
leaking or about revealing the name the
name was never made public in any event
it was about whistleblowing and it was
because I aired the cia's dirty laundry
and I said the CIA was torturing its
prisoners and so I went to prison for 23
months for violating the intelligence
identities protection act I'm only the
second American ever to be charged with
that crime and I'm the only CIA officer
ever to go to prison for speaking to the
Press
would you do it again oh in a heartbeat
in a heartbeat see this is this is the
thing the American people have the right
to know what the government is doing in
their name and it is illegal to classify
a crime I believed at the time I still
believe today that torture is illegal
and so to classify that torture program
as some kind of a top secret
compartmented program is illegal I stand
by that
I wanted to get your response to this
latest news a federal judge has cleared
the way for a trial against two military
psychologists who helped devise the bush
administration's interrogation program
which included using torture as
waterboarding the psychologist James
Mitchell and Bruce jessen reaped more
than 80 million dollars for Designing
torture techniques used by the agency
the lawsuit was brought by Suleiman
Abdullah Saleem and Mohammed been sued
two survivors of the torture program
along with the family of Rodman who
wrote who froze to death at a CIA back
site in Afghanistan I'm wondering your
uh your reaction
I'm thrilled about this lawsuit and
frankly I can't believe that both the
Obama administration's CIA leadership
and the Trump Administration CIA
leadership have allowed this case to go
forward one of the things that's truly
sickening about this case is that the
psychologist Mitchell and Jess and just
in the last two weeks used the example
of of scientists in Nazi Germany who
developed zyclon B gas that was used to
gas Jews in concentration camps as part
of their defense they said that at
Nuremberg the inventors of zyklon B
weren't prosecuted so they shouldn't be
prosecuted because they only taught the
CIA how to torture that's just simply
not true
the scientists that invented the zyclon
B were not prosecuted but but Mitchell
and Jess and not just created this
torture program they went overseas to
the secret site to the secret prison and
they were the ones who actually carried
out the torture I think frankly that
Mitchell and jessen are very very
fortunate in that this is not a criminal
trial because this is a violation their
actions are a violation of the federal
torture Act of 1946 and a violation of
the United Nations
conventions Against torture so they're
lucky I think that this is only a civil
suit
well John cariakou we want to thank you
very much for being with us Jones spent
14 years at the CIA as an adolescent
case officer he exposed the bushira
torture program became the only official
jailed in connection with it his Memoir
is doing time like a spy how the CIA
taught me to survive and thrive in
prison this is democracy now when we
come back we go to Minneapolis where a
mosque was bombed this weekend president
Trump has been tweeting up a storm on
his vacation not a word about this act
of what the Minnesota Governor is
calling terrorism stay with us